你们好黑客
hello hackers
欢迎回到
welcome back to
逆向工程模块的新一集
another episode and the reverse engineering module
今天我们将讨论数据访问
today we're going to be talking about data access
具体来说，不同内存区内不同数据的不同访问方式
specifically how different access of different data in different regions looks like
让我解释一下
um let me show you what I mean as a reminder
数据可以分布在很多不同的内存区域
data can be in a lot of different regions
它可以在.data中用于预初始化全局数据
it can be in .data for pre initialized global data
在.rodata中用于只读全局数据
and .rodata for global data that is read only
和在.BSS中用于未初始化全局数据
and .BSS for global data that does not have an initial state
所以它实际上不需要在ELF文件中
so it doesn't need to actually be in the ELF file
它被映射到一个MC（内存块）
it gets mapped into an MC chunk of memory
它可以在栈中
it can be in the stack
栈我们在之前的视频中讨论过
and we've discussed that in previous video
用于静态分配局部变量
used for statically allocated local variable
数据可以在使用malloc动态分配的堆中
it can be in the heap for dynamically allocated data using malloc
然后用free等函数来释放
and then freed using free and so forth
这个我们将在
this one we'll explore in
之后的课程中探讨
later in the course
我们在此不讨论堆
we won't talk about the heap
并且不需要与堆进行太多交互
much or you won't have to interact with the heap much
因为它有自己的安全问题，我们以后会
because it has its own security issues that we'll
深入研究
go in depth into
让我们先看看这些不同区域的数据是如何被访问的
but let's look at how data in these different regions is accessed
从栈开始
starting from the stack
栈上的数据通常是通过push和pop来访问的
so data on the stack is typically accessed using push and pop
或者使用栈指针+偏移量
or using stack pointer relative addresses
或者使用基指针+偏移量
or using base pointer relative addresses of course
从左边的栈指针（访问栈帧内数据）
um from the stack pointer which is on on the left of the stack
地址是（口误）
the addresses are
偏移量是正数
the offsets are positive
因为栈帧位于栈指针和
because the stack frame goes between the stack pointer
栈帧指针 或者叫 基指针之间（rsp和rbp之间）
and the frame slash base pointer
从栈指针开始，偏移量为正数
from the stack pointer the offsets are positive
是在内存中向前
because we're going forward in memory
通过基指针访问，偏移量为负数
from the base pointer the offsets are negative
因为我们是朝着栈指针走（在内存中向后）
because we are going backwards towards the stack pointer
这里有一些例子
all right here are some examples
用同样的方式引用
that you the same way to reference
如果栈指针指向这个
if the stack pointer is pointing to this
抱歉，我的鼠标没有指向这个区域
sorry my mouse wasn't showing to this area right here
你可以
you can
通过解引用RSP来访问它
access this by dereferencing RSP
或者解引用RBP减去0x28
or dereferencing RBP minus ox 28
这是RSP + 0x8， RBP - 0x20等等
and this is RSP plus ox8 and RBP minus ox 20 and so on
好
right
哦 这很
cool that's
漂亮
pretty
有趣
interesting
有多种方法，还有一种方法
multiple ways there's actually one more way of course
你可以把RSP或RBP的值赋值给其他
you can get the value of RSP or RBP into some other
叫什么来着，其他变量，然后
what's it called some other variable and then
解引用那个变量
dereference that variable
这就有点棘手了（对于逆向）
this makes it a little tricky
因为仅凭这个很难分辨
because it's hard to tell from just this memory store
数据是否被存储在栈上
that things are being stored onto the stack
你还需要仔细理解
you need to then also carefully understand
RDX是在哪里被设置的
where RDX got set
这完全可以在另一个函数中
which could have been in another function altogether
这就很复杂了
so it gets pretty complicated
这些通常就是访问栈上数据的方式
but typically this is how data on the stack is accessed
如何访问ELF 节中的数据呢
what about data in ELF sections
有趣的是
well the interesting things
所有这些ELF节，BSS， rodata
all these ELF sections BSS rodata
和. data
and .data
它们存储在ELF文件中或直接映射在
they are stored in the ELF file or mapped directly
ELF文件后
after the ELF file
所以他们
so they are
始终距离程序代码一段已知偏移量
always a known offset away from the program code
它们通过rip相对寻址来访问
and they are accessed using rip relative addressing
比如从内存中加载数据到寄存器
to load you would you know
做像这些指令之类的操作
do something along these lines
将rip+通常不大的数字（可能在想代码段和数据段相邻）指向的内存数据加载到RAX
move into RAX from rip plus some usually not large number
因为
because
如果我们倒回去
if we rewind
你仔细看这些地址
and you look very closely at these addresses
基本上这里发生的是
basically what happens here is
这个程序
the program
映射到内存两次
is mapped into memory twice
一次是代码段，一次是
once for the code and once
完全分开的
completely separately
在代码段后面一点的所有的数据段
a little bit later for all of the data segments
所以在这段代码中是
and so the code and data segments are
跨内存段访问数据（从代码段中访问数据段）
accessed from 2 different areas
尽管是同一份文件
even though it's from the same file
所以它是rip加上一些大的偏移（这里说大，强调跨内存段了）
so it's it's rip plus some large offset
Store操作显然是一样的
store is obviously the same
当然了也
and then of course
可以使用load effective address（lea）来获得它的内存地址
you can get a reference to it by using load effective address
当然这会变的棘手（对逆向来说）
and then of course this is tricky
之后你可以解引用rax
then later on you can dereference Rax
然后你要思考RAX是从哪里来的
and then you have to think where is RAX coming from
通过找哪个函数调用了这个函数
by going understanding what calls that function
在你逆向的程序中
that you're reverse engineering and so on
好的，堆
alright the heap
在这一讲中，我们不会过多地讨论堆
again we're not gonna look at the heap very much in this module
但是我们稍后会详细地讨论这个堆
but we will look at the heap a lot later
在这里我们将学习如何访问
and here we'll learn how to look at
从堆中返回的数据
data that is being returned by the heap from the heap
通常
typically
你有一个通过malloc获取的指针
you have a pointer that you retrieve via malloc
然后你需要
and then you need to
把它存在某处
store it somewhere
无论是在栈中，在另一个全局变量中
whether that is on the stack in another global variable
还是在寄存器中
or in a register
这可能会很棘手
and this can get pretty tricky
如果你看这里，我有两个例子
I mean if you look here I have 2 examples
例子一是栈数据访问
example one is a stack data access right where
我们将栈指针赋值给Rax，然后解引用Rax
we are moving the stack pointer to Rax and then dereferencing Rax
这个可以访问这里的数据
and this accesses this data right here
另一种是任意数据访问
the other one is an arbitrary data access
,由于
by due
引用存储在栈上的指针
referencing a pointer that's stored on the stack
唯一不同的是这些方括号
and all that's different are these square brackets
这里我们在栈指针处解引用数据
so here we are dereferencing the data at the stack pointer
这个数据
this data
抱歉，数据存储在栈顶部
sorry the data stored at the top of the stack
我们解引用这个数据
we're dereferencing this data
赋值给rax，然后解引用它
moving into rax and then dereferencing that
然后将数据读入RDX
and then reading this data into RDX
两个区别明显的不同操作
two very important different operations
后者你更有可能看到
this is something that you're more likely to see
例如
with for example
访问从堆返回的数据
data return from the heap
好吧
alright
最后谈谈数据结构
finally a word about data structures
当你编写代码时，你可能会创建结构体
when you're writing code you might create structs
对象
objects
不同类型变量的复杂组合
complex combinations of variables of different types
所有这些信息在编译过程中都会丢失
all of this information is lost in the compilation process
你得把这些拼凑起来
you're gonna have to piece that together
基于数据的访问方式
based on how data is accessed
储存方式，使用方式
how it's stored and how it's used
这并不容易
it's not easy
我还没有找到一个好办法
and I have not found a good way
把这些知识传达给你们
to just convey this knowledge to you
你要做的是
the way that you're going to do it
解决一个又一个逆向练习
is tackle reversing problem after reversing problem
直到
until
你理解
you understand
但你会成功的
but you'll get there
下节课见
see you next video